Finding Aid for the Cole Family Papers LSC.0217
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Correspondence of Cornelius Cole, 1851-1924; (Approximately 4000 pieces)
  - Cornelius Cole to Olive Cole, 1868-1872
    - 1869, 18 pieces. (Box 7)
      Letters written from Washington, D.C., en route overland, Sacramento concerning the completion of the Pacific railroad, Grant, San Domingo, Chicago, Omaha, Albert D. Richardson, the journalist.
    - 1870, 42 pieces. (Box 7)
      Letters written from Washington, D.C. concerning the Franco-Prussian war, debates in the Senate on the sugar tariff, Southern Pacific Railroad bill, San Domingo treaty, John Sherman, Schuyler Colfax, Samoan Islands, Naturalization legislation, Cole's daily conferences with Grant and Secretary of the Treasury George Boutwell, the recall of John Motley, Grant's character, Samuel L. Clemens.
    - 1871, 9 pieces. (Box 7)
      Letters written from Washington, D.C. and elsewhere concerning Ku Klux Klan bill, the Grant family, Ogden, Utah.
    - 1872, 65 pieces. (Box 7)
      Letters written from Washington, D.C. concerning amendments to the Treaty of Washington, Zachariah Chandler, Benjamin Wade, reception at the Japanese ministry, Mormon leader Orson Pratt, dinner with Robert G. [?] Ingersoll, Carl Schurz, A.A. Sargent, Conkling's defense of Grant in the Senate, Charles Sumner's criticism of Grant, Ku Klux Klan bill, nomination of Grant, visit of Hamilton Fish to San Francisco, threat of war with England, Washington, D.C. society, pictures taken by Mathew Brady and Alexander Gardner.
  - Cornelius Cole to Olive Cole, 1873-1877
    - 1873, 10 pieces. (Box 8)
      Letters written from Washington concerning partisan factions in the Senate and Washington, D.C., the Cabinet, Senate campaign in California concerning Newton Booth and A.A. Sargent, William Evarts, William Belknap, the appointment of a Chief Justice, the Asiatic Commercial Company, Texas-Pacific railroad, Northern railroad, the Grant family.
    - 1874, 36 pieces. (Box 8)
      Letters written from California and Washington, D.C. concerning the A.A. Sargent Senatorial contest in California, affairs in Los Angeles, Nebraska, James Carleton of New Mexico Territory, Leland Stanford, General Edward Ord, Attorney General George Williams, dislike of Hamilton Fish for Cole and Fish's opposition to Cole, William T. Sherman and John Sherman, minister to Vienna, a currency bill, Senator William Stewart of Nevada, property of Grant in Midwest.
    - 1875, 37 pieces. (Box 8)
      Letters written from Washington, D.C. concerning the death of Andrew Johnson, John Sherman, Benjamin Bristow, Georgetown University, Cole as a possible appointee as Secretary of the Interior, migrations to California, life in Nevada, economic and political state of the nation, various candidates of both parties.
    - 1876, 42 pieces. (Box 8)
      Letters written from Washington, D.C. concerning the presidential campaign, the Geneva Award bill, the Centennial Exposition at Philadelphia, the contested election, debates in Congress on the Amnesty bill, Senator George Edmunds, Grant's Cabinet, slender victory of the Republican Presidential candidate, reception of the Belknap scandal in Washington, D.C., the War Premiums bill, settlement of the Alabama claims, Secretary of the Interior Zachariah Chandler, Benjamin Wade.
    - 1877, 32 pieces. (Box 8)
      Letters written from Sacramento, Los Angeles, voyage in the Caribbean Sea, Washington, D.C. concerning state and local affairs in California, Democratic and Republican factions during the electoral crisis, John Sherman on the Joint Committee for the election, Cole's confidence in the victory of Rutherford B. Hayes, presence of foreigners on ship in the Caribbean Sea.
  - Cornelius Cole to Olive Cole, 1878-1883
    - 1878, 52 pieces. (Box 9)
      Letters written from Los Angeles and San Francisco concerning local and family matters, specifically, real estate.
    - 1879-1881, 10 pieces. (Box 9)
      Letters written from San Francisco concerning family matters.
    - 1882, 51 pieces. (Box 9)
      Letters written from San Francisco concerning the Alabama Claims bill, President Chester A. Arthur, Garfield's assassin, Charles Guiteau, Tax-Payer's Anti-Monopoly campaign.
    - 1883, 98 pieces. (Box 9)
      Letters written from San Francisco concerning the influence of the Southern Pacific railroad on state politics, General William T. Sherman's visit to San Francisco and his possibilities as a candidate for President, the publication of the Collis P. Huntington letters.
  - Cornelius Cole to Olive Cole, 1884-1886
    - 1884, 133 pieces. (Box 10)
      Letters written from Washington, D.C. concerning James G. Blaine and Grover Cleveland, the Court of Claims for the Alabama cases, a meeting with Chester A. Arthur, the Arthur Cabinet, John A. Logan, General and Mrs. Sherman, Senator Shelby Cullom of Illinois, members and former members of the Senate, Kansas, California campaigns, oration by Robert Ingersoll, the financial failure of the Grants.
    - 1885, 78 pieces. (Box 10)
      Letters written from San Francisco, Boston, Washington, D.C., concerning the last illness of Grant, Columbian celebration by Italians in San Francisco, lectures by Joseph Le Conte and John Fiske, the French spoliation claims, the bequest of Leland Stanford, Boston and New England people, Women's Suffrage Association.
    - 1886, 70 pieces. (Box 10)
      Letters written from Sacramento and San Francisco, concerning China problems, Chinese exclusion, the land rush to San Diego and Los Angeles, Southern Pacific railroad's monopoly of San Francisco traffic, Grand Army of the Republic Convention in San Francisco, John A. Logan and his wife, William T. Sherman and his wife, Grant and his Memoirs.
  - Cornelius Cole to Olive Cole, 1887-1916
    - 1887, 103 pieces.
      Letters written from San Francisco concerning the Southern Pacific railroad's control of state politics, northern California discrimination against Los Angeles citrus growers, clemency for the Chicago anarchists, lecture by John Hittell, concert by Adela Patti.
    - 1890, 41 pieces. (Box 11)
      Letters written from San Francisco concerning San Francisco's apprehension over the Los Angeles land boom, the 40th anniversary of statehood celebration, Society of California Pioneers.
    - 1892, 7 pieces. (Box 11)
      Letters written from Colegrove, Los Angeles, concerning family matters, James G. Blaine's memoirs.
    - 1895-1896, 33 pieces. (Box 11)
      Letters written from Washington, D.C. concerning the debates and lobbies in Congress over the Los Angeles Harbor bill, strategy and efforts of supporters of San Pedro and Santa Monica sites, Senators Stephen M. White of California, Edmunds of Vermont, Schurz, the changes in the capitol city, the Chicago Republican National Convention, William McKinley, influence of the Southern Pacific railroad on persons and politics in California, St. Louis, East St. Louis tornado, Collis P. Huntington in Washington, D.C., visit to President Cleveland by Cole, Louisiana, Texas.
    - 1916, 8 pieces. (Box 11)
      Letters written from Colegrove, Los Angeles, concerning Theodore Roosevelt's candidacy at the Republican National Convention in Chicago.
  - Olive Cole to Cornelius Cole, 1852-1868
    - 1852-1853, 18 pieces. (Box 12)
      Letters written from Santa Cruz, California and elsewhere concerning family affairs.
    - 1853-1861, 19 pieces. (Box 12)
      Letters written from Santa Cruz, California, concerning local and family affairs.
    - 1862, 80 pieces. (Box 12)
      Letters written from Santa Cruz and elsewhere, concerning family affairs, McClellan and the Emancipation Proclamation.
    - 1863, 25 pieces. (Box 12)
      Letters written from Santa Cruz and elsewhere concerning local and family affairs, celebration of the victory at Vicksburg.
    - 1864, 35 pieces. (Box 12)
      Letters written from Trumansburg, New York and elsewhere, concerning the nomination of McClellan, the course of the war, Benjamin F. Butler, Reverdy Johnson, Andersonville prison.
    - 1865, 42 pieces. (Box 12)
      Letters written from Havana, New York and elsewhere concerning family affairs, Negro freedmen.
    - 1866, 25 pieces. (Box 12)
      Letters written from Geneva, New York and Trumansburg, New York concerning Andrew Johnson.
    - 1867, 31 pieces. (Box 12)
      Letters written from Washington, D.C. concerning state elections, the trial of George W. Cole, Baron de Stoeckl and Russian affairs, Roscoe Conkling.
    - 1868, 30 pieces. (Box 12)
      Letters written from Washington, D.C. concerning the impeachment of Andrew Johnson, John Conness as possible Secretary of the Interior, the marriage of Robert T. Lincoln, Grant, Colfax.
  - Olive Cole to Cornelius Cole, 1870-1881
    - 1870, 30 pieces. (Box 13)
      Letters written from Washington, D.C. concerning members of the Senate, Hamilton Fish, John L. Motley, the Grant family.
    - 1871-1872, 64 pieces. (Box 13)
      Letters written from Washington, D.C., San Francisco concerning the Central Pacific Railroad's influence in California politics and the Republican State Convention, Alaska, Charles Sumner, Carl Schurz, Grant and his supporters in California, Secretary of the Interior Columbus Delano, Frederick Dent.
    - 1873, 18 pieces. (Box 13)
      Letters written from San Francisco concerning the Senate campaign of Newton Booth, the influence of the Central Pacific Railroad in California politics, Benjamin Bristow.
    - 1874, 27 pieces. (Box 13)
      Letters written from San Francisco and elsewhere concerning the Sanborn contracts, General William T. Sherman, Grant.
    - 1875, 55 pieces. (Box 13)
      Letters written from San Francisco and elsewhere concerning California politics, Hubert H. Bancroft at Lake Tahoe.
    - 1876, 46 pieces. (Box 13)
      Letters written mainly from Sacramento concerning the candidates, parties, and events in the national election, the Centennial Exposition at Philadelphia, the trial of William Belknap.
    - 1877, 9 pieces. (Box 13)
      Letters written from California concerning family matters.
    - 1878, 11 pieces. (Box 13)
      Letters written from California concerning the Grant family.
    - 1879-1881, 13 pieces. (Box 13)
      Letters written from California concerning the Cabinet of James A. Garfield.
  - Olive Cole to Cornelius Cole, 1882-1916
    - 1882, 27 pieces. (Box 14)
      Letters written from California concerning local and family affairs.
    - 1883, 22 pieces. (Box 14)
    - 1884, 70 pieces. (Box 14)
      Letters written from Colegrove, Los Angeles, concerning local and family affairs, the national election, James G. Blaine, James Harlan, possible appointments by Grover Cleveland.
    - 1885, 52 pieces. (Box 14)
      Letters written from Colegrove, Los Angeles, concerning state politics, the election of Leland Stanford as Senator.
    - 1886, 8 pieces. (Box 14)
      Letters written from Colegrove, Los Angeles concerning family matters.
    - 1887, 8 pieces. (Box 14)
      Letters written from Colegrove, Los Angeles, concerning family matters.
    - 1916, 14 pieces. (Box 14)
      Letters written from Chicago and elsewhere concerning events and persons at the Republican National Convention in Chicago where Olive Cole was Delegate at Large from California, Theodore Roosevelt, Charles E. Hughes, Theodore E. Burton of Ohio, General Leonard Wood.
  - Correspondence of Cornelius Cole With Members of His Family, 1851-1924
    - Cornelius Cole to his children, 1862-1923; 28 pieces. (Box 15, Folder 1)
      There are letters to Emma, Seward, Willoughby, Grace, George R., George Townsend, Cornelia concerning Samuel L. Clemens, suffragettes, financial conditions before the election of 1896, location of Cole's copy of the Emancipation Proclamation.
    - Cornelius Cole to his mother and sister Martha., 1851-1863; 8 pieces. (Box 15, Folder 2)
      Concerning fires in San Francisco in 1852
    - George W. Cole to Cornelius Cole, 1863-1879; 53 pieces. (Box 15, Folder 3)
      Concerning Headquarters, Department of Virginia and North Carolina, army campaigns, Dutch Gap canal failure, rams and torpedoes on the James River, the military situation in Virginia in January 1865, Fortress Monroe, Negro troops, freed slaves, controversy over promotion involving Benjamin F. Butler, Salmon P. Chase, Edwin Stanton, impeachment of Andrew Johnson, Mexico Granada mail contract, Atchison, Topeka railroad, Santa Fe, New Mexico, to San Francisco railroad, arrest and trial of George W. Cole, mining and railroads in New Mexico Territory.
    - Father, brothers and sisters to Cornelius Cole, 1852-1910; 65 pieces. (Box 15, Folder 4)
      Letters from David, Gilbert M., Elijah Cole, Mary Stewart, Lourina Severns, Kate Nivison, concerning Gilbert Cole's voyage to California in 1848-1849, William M. Evarts, Fort Union, New Mexico Territory.
    - Sons and daughters to Cornelius Cole, 1864-1924; 130 pieces. (Box 15, Folder 5)
      Letters from Seward, Lucretia, Willoughby, Grace, Cornelia, Mary, Emma, George Townsend, concerning Cornell University, the Grant family, Republican politics in New Mexico.
    - Various relatives to Cornelius Cole, 1868-1923; 36 pieces. (Box 15, Folder 6)
      Including letters from nephews David Cole, Frank Cole, Frank A. Smith, Charles H. Stewart, Paul Marlow, Charles C. Smith; nieces Helen Nivison, Anna Boyer; cousins J.M. Townsend, Frank Stewart; niece Adela Cole; brother-in-law S.C. Colegrove; grandsons Willoughby and Gregory Cole; concerning industry in Arizona, northern Mexico and the Rio Grande country.
    - Various relatives to Cornelius Cole, 1908-1924; 70 pieces. (Box 15, Folder 7)
      Letters from nephew C.C. Smith concerning superintendency of Sequoia and Yosemite National Parks, letters concerning Cole family and ancestry, property in New Mexico.
- Correspondence of the Cole Family, 1846-1940; (Approximately 1700 pieces)
  - Correspondence of Olive Cole With Various Persons, 1851-1918
    - 1852-1918, 20 pieces. (Box 16)
      Drafts and copies of letters to various persons including Benjamin F. Butler, Ulysses S. Grant, James G. Blaine, concerning a Cabinet appointment for Cornelius Cole, to Senator James E. Watson concerning Theodore Roosevelt, Hiram Johnson, and the Progressive Party in 1918; Letter concerning Senator George H. Williams as Secretary of Interior; Letter concerning the Blaines [????], [????], changes in the capital.
    - 1851-1869, 92 pieces. (Box 16)
      Letters to Olive Cole from various persons including letters from James Pratt, letter from John Augustus Sutter, 1867, and letters from various friends and relatives concerning the transfer of Indian Affairs to the War Department, the trial of George Cole, letter from Benjamin F. Butler.
    - 1870-1880, 60 pieces. (Box 16)
      Letters to Olive Cole from various relatives and friends, letter from John Bidwell concerning the Independent Party of 1875, telegram from Ulysses S. Grant concerning visit of Willoughby Cole, invitation from Julia Dent Grant, clippings concerning Nellie Grant, 3 letters from Ellen Ewing Sherman, letter from Admiral Parrott, letter from J.M. Cutt, the brother-in-law of Stephen A. Douglas, letter from Julia Dent Grant.
    - 1881-1889, 8 pieces. (Box 16)
      Letters to Olive Cole from various relatives and friends, including letter from Samuel Purdy concerning James G. Blaine.
    - 3 letters to Olive Cole from Warren Harding., 1916-17 (Box 16)
  - Various Persons to Olive Cole, 1892-1893
    - 1892, 110 pieces. (Box 17)
      Letters and papers from various persons to Olive Cole mainly concerning the World's Columbian Exposition at Chicago, and other expositions in California at the same time. Olive Cole was one of the Lady Managers of California's exhibits at the Exposition.
    - 1893, 145 pieces. (Box 17)
      A continuation of the subject matter from the preceding folder, with the addition of letters from various persons concerning Olive Cole's resignation as manager of the California exhibit at the Columbian Exposition.
  - Various Persons to Olive Cole, 1894-1922
    - 1894-1913, 62 pieces. (Box 18)
      Letters from various relatives and friends concerning abolition days, Women's National Silver League. 4 letters from Mrs. John A. Logan.
    - 1914-1915, 64 pieces. (Box 18)
      Letters from various relatives and friends concerning the Historical Society of Southern California, women's suffrage, Los Angeles, state Republican campaigns, letter from Mrs. John A. Logan.
    - 1916, 150 pieces. (Box 18)
      Letters from relatives, friends, and various persons to Olive Cole concerning local, state, and national political campaigns, the Republican Convention at Chicago.
    - 1917-1922, 13 pieces. (Box 18)
      Letters from various persons to Olive Cole, including letter from Nicholas Murray Butler, Senator Watson Squire of Oregon, card from Mrs. John A. Logan.
    - Undated, 33 pieces. (Box 18)
      Letters from various persons to Olive Cole concerning Columbus Delano and Mrs. Delano, note from Jessie B. Fremont, letter from Jesse Grant.
  - Olive Cole to Members of the Cole Family, 1853-1904
    - Letters from Olive Cole to her children, 1875-1912; 23 pieces. (Box 19, Folder 1)
      Including letters to Emma, Seward, Schuyler Lucretia, concerning family matters.
    - Letters from Olive Cole to her son George R. Cole, 1892-1897; 90 pieces. (Box 19, Folder 2)
      Concerning family matters, Los Angeles and California affairs, with occasional references to national events.
    - Letters from Olive Cole to her son George R. Cole, 1898-1899; 50 pieces. (Box 19, Folder 3)
      Concerning family, local, and occasional national affairs.
    - Letters from Olive Cole to her son George R. Cole, 1900-1904; 70 pieces. (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Olive Cole to her sisters Martha and Susan Colegrove, 1853-1859; 4 pieces. (Box 19, Folder 5)
      Concerning politics in Sacramento.
    - Olive Cole to her cousin, Carrie, 1851-1856; 10 pieces. (Box 19, Folder 6)
      Letters written from New York and California, concerning family affairs in Sacramento.
  - Correspondence of Olive Cole With Her Children, 1871-1916
    - Letters from Olive Cole to her son George R. Cole, 1905-1916; 140 pieces. (Box 20, Folder 1)
      Concerning family and local matters, and occasional references to national affairs.
    - Children to Olive Cole, 1871-1907; 130 pieces. (Box 20, Folder 2)
      Letters from Lucretia, Nellie, Emma, Seward, Willoughby, concerning Cornell University and the Grant family, Schuyler, George R.
  - Members of the Cole Family to Olive Cole, 1846-1900
    - Letters to Olive Cole from her father, A.C. Colegrove, written from Trumansburg, New York., 1853-1862; 19 pieces. (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Letters to Olive Cole from her brother Brad T. Colegrove and her brother-in-law James Pratt., 1853-1868; 13 pieces. (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - Letters to Olive Cole from her brother Silas Colegrove, written from Santa Cruz, California, Burdett and Trumansburg, New York., 1852-1868; 38 pieces. (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Letters to Olive Cole from her brother-in-law George W. Cole., 1862-1867; 17 pieces. (Box 21, Folder 4)
      Concerning his military career, his imprisonment and trial.
    - Letters to Olive Cole from her sister Katherine Colegrove., 1853-1891; 68 pieces. (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Letters to Olive Cole from her sister Susan Colegrove., 1846-1878; 98 pieces. (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Letters to Olive Cole from her sisters Caroline, Mollie, and her sisters-in-law, Martha, Mary, and Lourina., 1844-1887; 92 pieces. (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - Letters to Olive Cole from her various relatives, 1853-1900; 20 pieces. (Box 21, Folder 8)
      Including letters from her niece Helen Nivison, and her nephew David Cole concerning mining in Arizona Territory.
  - Correspondence of Willoughby Cole, 1877-1912
    - Willoughby Cole to various persons., 1878-1912; 10 pieces. (Box 50, Folder 1)
      Drafts and copies of letters to T.F. Bayard, Ulysses S. Grant Jr., Jesse Grant, and Frank P. Flint.
    - Various persons to Willoughby Cole., 1877-1903; 34 pieces. (Box 50, Folder 2)
      Letters from Thomas F. Bayard concerning claims against the Mexican government, letter from Frank P. Flint concerning the pardon of two Indians, 3 telegrams and 3 letters from Jesse Grant concerning personal matters and mining investments, letters concerning W. Cole's legal practice.
    - Various persons to Willoughby Cole., 1904-1909; 40 pieces. (Box 50, Folder 3)
      Letters concerning W. Cole's legal and financial business, letter from Ulysses S. Grant Jr. concerning personal matters, 14 letters from Jesse Grant concerning personal matters, his political plans, before and during the campaign of 1908, C. Cole's connection with Alaska purchase.
    - Various persons to Willoughby Cole., 1910-1912; 25 pieces. (Box 50, Folder 4)
      Letters concerning W. Cole's finances and property.
  - Correspondence and Papers of Seward Cole, 1874-1916
    - Seward Cole to various persons., 1878-1916; 5 pieces. (Box 50, Folder 5)
      Letters concerning S. Cole's business and property interests.
    - Business papers of Seward Cole., 1874-1876; 15 pieces. (Box 50, Folder 6)
      Papers and documents concerning Salamander Felting company.
    - Various persons to Seward Cole., 1888-1916; 25 pieces. (Box 50, Folder 7)
      Letters concerning citrus industry in California, attitude of the West on economic problems and currency issues 1894, irrigation of California lands, S. Cole property improvements.
  - Correspondence of the Cole Family, 1847-1940
    - Letters from members of the Cole family to each other, including letters from Willoughby, George R., Gilbert, Emma, of the Coles, and from Caroline and Susan Colegrove., 1869-1916; 13 pieces. (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - Letters from various persons to members of the Cole family., 1847-1940; 32 pieces. (Box 22, Folder 2)
      Letters from the Los Angeles Chamber of Commerce concerning the death of Cornelius Cole, to Lucretia Cole Waring concerning her father's papers, his connection with the Alaska Purchase, letters from Catherine C. Phillips to Lucretia Cole Waring concerning research for her biography of Cornelius Cole. Also, 6 letters to George R. Cole from Claval Elemens 1 from Olivia Ellemens.
    - Manuscript pieces partly in the handwriting of Cornelius Cole, 11 pieces. (Box 22, Folder 3)
      Apparently attempts to communicate with deceased members of the Cole family.
    - Documents of the Cole Family Ancestors, 1819-1851; 36 pieces. (Box 22, Folder 4)
      Deeds, indentures, maps, titles, notices concerning the lands and properties primarily of David Cole, father of Cornelius Cole.
  - Correspondence of Lucretia Cole (Mrs. Howard S. Waring)
    - Lucretia Cole to Cornelius Cole., 1908-1909; 4 pieces. (Box 51, Folder 1)
    - Lucretia Cole to Olive Cole., 1871-1907; 42 pieces. (Box 51, Folder 2)
      Letters written from various places in Europe during two tours of the continent.
    - Lucretia Cole to Olive Cole., 1908-1909; 85 pieces. (Box 51, Folder 3)
      Letters written from various places in Europe.
    - Relatives to Lucretia Cole., 1893-1918; 26 pieces. (Box 51, Folder 4)
      Letters from sister Emma, brothers George T. and Schuyler, S.C. Colegrove, concerning death of Mr. Waring and of Olive Cole
  - Correspondence and Papers of Lucretia Cole
    - Various persons to Lucretia Cole., 1882-1893; 84 pieces. (Box 52, Folder 1)
      Letters from Gerard Leigh Hunt, Georgina Jones, 2 letters from Lizzie C. (Mrs. Frederick D.)Grant, concerning the death of Mr. Waring.
    - Various persons to Lucretia Cole., 1894-1946; 36 pieces. (Box 52, Folder 2)
      Letters from Europe, and letters concerning the family, including letter from Myron T. Herrick.